

#### **CONTACT ME AT**

+57 3163267456

alexandergribenchenko@gmail.com

in linkedin.com/in/alexandergribenchenko

github.com/alexandergribenchenko

Cali, Colombia

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

• PROGRAMMING LENGUAGES

Pyhton, SQL and MATLAB

#### DATA SCIENCE TOOLKITS

Jupyter, Numpy, Pandas, MatplotLib, Seaborn, Statsmodels, Sklearn, XGBoost, Keras, NLTK, spaCy, GitHub, PostgreSQL, Azure (Databricks, Data Factory), AWS (EC2, RDS, S3), PySpark, Power BI, Tableau

# • AI TECHNIQUES

Decision Trees, k-Nearest Neighboors (KNN), Linear and Polynomial Regression, Random Forest, Neural Networks, Natural Lenguage Procesing (NLP), k-Means, Singular Value Decomposition (SVD), Principal Component Analysis (PCA).

#### LENGUAGES

- Spanish: native lenguage
- English: Certified B2 according to the Common European Framework of reference (CEFR)
- Portuguese: Certified B1 according to the Common European
   Framework of reference (CEFR)

# **ALEXANDER ORTEGA**

# DATA SCIENTIST PHYSICIST MSC. ACOUSTICS AND VIBRATIONS

#### PERSONAL PROFILE

Data Scientists with experience collecting, analyzing, interpreting and performing data management tasks. Specific experience in the evaluation, automation, development and deployment of analytical models.

Knowledge in Big Data tools/solutions for advanced analytics and machine learning processes in cloud. Strengths in SQL and Python libraries, and developing Databricks notebooks for analytical purposes. Knowledge on visualization and reporting tools (Power BI and Tableau).

Great analytical and mathematical ability applied in the development of data analysis models. Bachelor's degree in Physics, and Master's degree in Acoustics and Vibrations.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### Data Scientist

TCS - Tata Consultancy Services | May 2021 - Present

- Evaluation, automation, development and deployment of analytical models for the areas of operations planning and digital marketing associated with the aeronautical industry.
- Translate the needs of different business areas into analytical solutions that allow obtaining quantitative and qualitative business insights and improve decisionmaking.

# Data Analyst - Acoustic Engineer

Alcaldía de Cali, Departamento Administrativo de Gestión del Medio Ambiente - DAGMA | Aug 2016 - Jun 2020

- Developed the methodology and programming for the evaluation and analysis of environmental noise in Santiago de Cali from the data provided by the noise monitoring stations in the city.
- Monthly generated the environmental noise evaluation and analysis section of the environmental quality bulletin published by the city's environmental authority.

# PERSONAL SKILLS

#### COMMUNICATION

Active listening, public speaking, effective writing

#### • ANALYTICAL

Critical thinking, curiosity, continuous learning, problem-solving

#### INTERPERSONAL

Teamworking, friendliness, confidence, encouraging

#### **HONORS & AWARDS**

- DS4A / Colombia 3.0: Graduated with Honors (2020):Outstanding Community Citizenship, and Outstanding Teamwork
- First Place & Scholarship Winner (Data Science for all Colombia 2020 V03)
- Master of Science, Acoustics and Vibrations Approved with distinction (2011)

#### LICENSES & CERTIFICATIONS

Azure Data Engineer Technologies for Beginners Udemy | Apr 2021

Complete Spark Course with Databricks (Big Data)
Coursera | Mar 2021

# Certification in Data Science (in progress)

Acámica (in colab. whit IBM and Globant) | Aug 2020 - Feb 2021

 This 7-month training program involves skills related to exploratory data analysis, feature engineering and the use of multiple machine learning models, as well as their applications in Natural Language Processing, Recommendation Systems, Image Analysis and Time Series.

# Data Science for All (DS4A / Colombia 3.0)

\* Graduated with honors: Outstanding Community Citizenship, and Outstanding Teamwork

Developed by Correlation One, sponsored by Ministry of Information and Communication Technologies. of Colombia - MinTIC. | Aug 2020 - Nov 2020

- Developed ClassiCode, a data science classification tool based on neural networks and NLP that make the state contracting processes for national government agencies more effective and efficient.
- ClassiCode was the winner among more than 107 projects presented throughout Colombia receiving a \$5,000 USD scholarship, as part of the Data Science For All - DS4A Colombia 2020 V3.0 program.

#### **EDUCATIONAL HISTORY**

# Master of Science, Acoustics and Vibrations

Universidad Austral de Chile | Dec 2010 - Dec 2011

- Approved with distiction
- Thesis involved numerical and computional skills using MATLAB to optimize the sound pressure radiation patterns of eliptic radiators.

# Bachelor of Science, Physics

Universidad del Valle, Cali, Colombia | Jan 2002 - Dec 2010

 Thesis involved numerical and computional skills using MATLAB for the determination of the acoustic field of 3D sound radiators.